<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts | Math/Stat Bio Group at ISU</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Posts</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2020 15:10:03 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Multilingual, and How to Keep It -- An Evolutionary Dynamics Perspective</title>
      <link>/post/why-multilingual-and-how-to-keep-it-an-evolutionary-dynamics-perspective/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2020 15:10:03 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/why-multilingual-and-how-to-keep-it-an-evolutionary-dynamics-perspective/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While many languages are in danger of extinction worldwide, multilingualism is being adopted for communication among different language groups, and playing a unique role of preserving language and cultural diversities. How multilingualism is developed and maintained therefore becomes an important interdisciplinary research subject for understanding complex social changes of modern-day societies. Here we consider a mixed population of multilingual speakers, with multilingual defined broadly as zero, limited, or full uses of multiple languages or dialects, and propose an evolutionary dynamic model for its development and evolution. The model consists of two different parts, formulated as two different evolutionary games. The first part accounts for selection of languages based on competition for population and social or economic preferences. The second part relates to circumstances when selection of languages is altered, for better or worse, by forces other than competition such as public policies, education, or family influences. By combining competition with intervention, we show how multilingualism may evolve under these two different sources of influences. We show in particular that by choosing appropriate interventional strategies, stable co-existence of languages, especially in multilingual forms, is possible, and extinction can be prevented, which is in contrast with major predictions from previous studies that co-existence of languages is unstable in general, and one language will eventually dominate the population while all others extinct.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title> Building a super organism: Social insects as models for studying the evolution of biological complexity</title>
      <link>/post/building-a-super-organism-social-insects-as-models-for-studying-the-evolution-of-biological-complexity/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Mar 2020 15:10:40 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/building-a-super-organism-social-insects-as-models-for-studying-the-evolution-of-biological-complexity/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social insects, such as ants, bees, wasps, and termites, have been important models for understanding complex systems. In this talk, I will provide an overview of my laboratory’s research program related to the mechanisms and evolution of highly social behavior in insects (called “eusociality”), focusing on bees and wasps. I will first describe a conceptual framework for the major cooperative transitions in evolution, along with a scenario for the evolution of eusociality in insects. I will provide some vignettes from my laboratory’s recent research studies that are contributing to our growing understanding of this major transition in evolution. We integrate studies of behavior, physiology, and genomics, and new insights are beginning to unravel how eusociality evolved, fueled by recent advances in genomics and applying these to multiple species, including honey bees, bumble bees, and paper wasps.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title> On large and small data blow-up solutions in the Classical Trojan Y- Chromosome Model</title>
      <link>/post/on-large-and-small-data-blow-up-solutions-in-the-classical-trojan-y-chromosome-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2020 15:10:40 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/on-large-and-small-data-blow-up-solutions-in-the-classical-trojan-y-chromosome-model/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trojan Y-Chromosome (TYC) strategy is a biological control used to cause the extinction of invasive fish populations by manipulating the populations sex ratio. This is done by introducing YY super males into the invasive population, which guarantees male progeny upon mating with the YY males. We consider a three species TYC model, and show that, if the introduction rate of trojan fish is zero, under certain large data assumptions, negative solutions are possible for the male population which can in turn lead to finite time blow-up in the female and male populations. In order to overcome this, we will propose models that possess globally existing non-negative solutions, in any parameter or initial data regime.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Paired-end reads merging using pair-hidden Markov model</title>
      <link>/post/paired-end-reads-merging-using-pair-hidden-markov-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2020 15:10:46 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/paired-end-reads-merging-using-pair-hidden-markov-model/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A DNA fragment, in Illumina paired-end (PE) sequencing, is read from both ends, resulting forward and backward reads. This can be seen as a challenge and also an opportunity to infer the DNA fragment by merging the information from the PE reads, where the alignment is involved is part of the solution. The challenge is identifying the replicate nucleotides and combining the information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There have been numerous tools developed for merging PE reads (and this area of research is still growing). Many of these methods ignore the possibility of sequencing indels, which are rare but not impossible, or assign penalties more consistent with evolutionary rates than Illuminated sequencing rates for indels. All of these methods either ignore the quality scores or assume they can be interpreted as PHRED error probabilities. Preliminary evidence suggests that using quality based substitution penalties and appropriate indel penalties in alignment can improve read pairmerging. We propose the idea of PE read merging via HMM. The alignment state is the hidden information at each site. The possible hidden states include non overlapping end regions and deletions, insertions, and match base pairs in the overlap region. We are building the scheme under a pair-hidden Markov model (pair-HMM) using the Baum-Welch algorithm to estimate the parameters, and the Viterbi algorithm to find the most likely alignment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Indirect Effects of Invasive Species</title>
      <link>/post/indirect-effects-of-invasive-species/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2020 15:10:55 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/indirect-effects-of-invasive-species/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Invasive species cause large scale damages to ecosystems because of direct effects of depredation and/or competition, with native species. However, sometimes they also effect ecosystems “indirectly”. In this talk, we will discuss recent work on the indirect effects of invasive ascidian species on crab-mussel predator-prey communities, in the gulf of Maine. We will also discuss the “indirect” control of pests, via boosting the efficiency of introduced predators, with additional food.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding the Rules of Life - Design Principles of Gene Regulatory Networks</title>
      <link>/post/test/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2020 15:10:08 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/test/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gene regulatory networks (GRNs) describe the gene-gene interactions within a cell and can be modeled using (generalized) Boolean networks. In this modeling framework, time and state (gene concentration level) are discretized, and an update rule determines the state of a gene based on the state of its regulators at the previous time step. Kauffman introduced canalizing functions as appropriate update rules for GRNs. In short, a canalizing function possesses at least one input such that, if this input takes on a certain “canalizing” value, then the output is already determined, irrespective of the values of the other inputs. Despite being heavily used, the true prevalence of canalization in GRNs has never been thoroughly assessed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this talk, I describe my ongoing efforts to establish a database of all published, expert-curated Boolean GRN models, which I then harness to identify the fundamental design principles, the Rules of Life, that underlie gene regulation. Apart from canalization, I focus on the impact of network structure and topology on network dynamics and stability.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The higher&#34; status language doesn’t always win: The fall of English in India and the rise of Hindi</title>
      <link>/post/the-higher-status-language-doesn-t-always-win-the-fall-of-english-in-india-and-the-rise-of-hindi/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/the-higher-status-language-doesn-t-always-win-the-fall-of-english-in-india-and-the-rise-of-hindi/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Kushani DeSilva&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;
Classical language dynamics explains language shift as a process in which speakers adopt a higher status language in lieu of a lower status language. This is well documented with English having out-competed languages such as Scottish Gaelic, Welsh and Mandarin. The 1961-1991 Indian censuses report a sharp increase in Hindi/English Bilinguals, suggesting that English is on the rise in India - and is out-competing Hindi. However, the 1991 - 2011 data shows that Bilingual numbers have saturated, while Monolingual Hindi speakers continue to rise exponentially. To capture this counter-intuitive dynamics, we propose a novel language dynamics model of interaction between Monolingual Hindi speakers and Hindi/English Bilinguals, which captures the Indian census data of the last 50 years with near perfect accuracy, outperforming the best known language dynamics models from the literature. We thus provide a first example of a lower status language having out competed a higher status language.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Community stability of ecological networks</title>
      <link>/post/community-stability-of-ecological-networks/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/community-stability-of-ecological-networks/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Audrey McCombs&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;
An ecological community can be represented as a network of species connected by interspecific interactions. Recent work by Kondoh and Mougi (2012, 2017) examines the role of interaction-type diversity on community stability. In particular, they investigate how, if at all, interaction-type diversity affects community stability. They found that a moderate mixture of antagonistic and mutualistic interactions can stabilize population dynamics, and that increasing community complexity leads to increased stability in a hybrid community. Rohr et al. (2014) study how network architecture affects community persistence. In their work, they tease apart the idea of “feasibility,” which they define as a community in which, “all species have a constant positive abundance over time,” from the idea of “stability,” which are the “conditions under which the system returns to the equilibrium point.” Natural communities must be both feasible and stable, and the numerical simulations described in their paper map regions of the parameter space that produce communities meeting both these conditions. In this talk, we will present several definitions of stability in the context of ecological networks, and discuss our ongoing attempts to first, replicate the model of Kondoh and Mougi, and second, update it using the considerations described by Rohr et al (2014).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Updating Quality Scores During HMM-based Correction of ILLUMINA Next Generation Sequencing</title>
      <link>/post/updating-quality-scores-during-hmm-based-correction-of-illumina-next-generation-sequencing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/updating-quality-scores-during-hmm-based-correction-of-illumina-next-generation-sequencing/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Haijuan Zhang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;
PREMIER -(PRobabilistic Error-correction using Markov Inference in Errored Reads) has an advantage over comparable error correctors because it is a fully probabilistic model. As a result, it is possible to directly estimate the probability of error after correcting the error in ILLUMINA Next Generation Sequencing. However, PREMIER does not update the quality score after error correction. Phred quality score is a measure of the quality of the identification of the nucleobases generated by automated DNA Sequencing. We propose and show a hypothesis that the updated quality score in PREMIER is closer to the Phred quality score than a un-update quality score.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Brief Overview of Meta-Analysis</title>
      <link>/post/a-brief-overview-of-meta-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/a-brief-overview-of-meta-analysis/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt;
Dr. Mark Kaiser
Slides is &lt;a href=&#34;/slides/metaanalysis.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Brief Overview of Meta-Analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meta-analysis is widely employed in the areas of both human and animal health. The basic issue is how one might combine information from a number of studies on the effect of some potential treatment or preventative measure. There are a number of issues that are not strictly statistical in nature but that have critical importance for the quality of a meta-analysis. We will identify some of these, but will not cover any of them in detail. The focus of the talk will be on the statistical problem of combining estimates of “effect” from a collection of studies. We will present the traditional approaches of what are called the “fixed effect” model and the “random effects” model. Finally, we will suggest a potentially open line of investigation in the area of meta-analysis that could be pursued for maybe a creative component.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Robust Continuous Clustering Reveals Hierarchical Structure in single cell RNA-seq data.</title>
      <link>/post/robust-continuous-clustering-reveals-hierarchical-structure-in-single-cell-rna-seq-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/robust-continuous-clustering-reveals-hierarchical-structure-in-single-cell-rna-seq-data/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Xiyu Peng&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Single cell RNA-seq has enabled researchers to investigate the complex population structure in a heterogeneous tissue. One important research question in the analysis of scRNA-Seq data is to identify cell subtypes with different gene expression profile. However, scRNA-seq data is high dimensional along with high noise. The common clustering strategy is to do clustering after dimension reduction or iteratively perform dimension reduction and clustering. We propose a novel clustering method joint with dimension reduction, in which dimension reduction and clustering are conducted simultaneously in the optimization. This is a robust extension of convex clustering, aiming to learn an embedding of cells into a low-dimensional space where clustering occurs. Moreover, the clustering path constructed via continuous clustering strategy can be viewed as an estimate of the developmental trajectories of cells, potentially reveal the underlying path for dynamic cellular processes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reconstructing Gene Co-expression Network with c-level Partial Correlation Graph</title>
      <link>/post/reconstructing-gene-co-expression-network-with-c-level-partial-correlation-graph/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/reconstructing-gene-co-expression-network-with-c-level-partial-correlation-graph/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt;
Hao Wang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slides is &lt;a href=&#34;/slides/hao_slides.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt;
Reconstructing Gene Co-expression Network with c-level Partial Correlation Graph&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;
A key aim in system biology is to understand molecules’ structural and functional processes in a living cell. With the development of high-throughput technologies, quantitative methods can be applied on the large scale ‘omics’ dataset. Due to the nature of intricate relationships of all molecules in a cell, network-based methods have become a popular approach to reconstruct gene-gene, gene-protein, and protein-protein interactions. Among different network approaches, Gaussian Graphical Model shows advantages in reconstructing gene co-expression networks because it is able to capture the direct association between genes with partial correlations. However, estimating and inferring partial correlations under the high-dimensional setting are very challenging. A method utilizing penalized partial correlations called exact hypothesis testing for shrinkage based Gaussian Graphical Models (Shrunk MLE) is able to overcome the high-dimension problem. However, the statistical inference of such penalized partial correlations is not satisfying. In this project, a novel network inference method, named c-level Partial Correlation Graph (c-level PCG), is applied to the gene expression dataset to model gene-gene direct association. It overcomes the ill-condition of p greater than n and successfully infers estimated partial correlation with false discovery rate controlled. Compared to Shrunk MLE, c-level PCG is able to achieve much higher statistical power and control the false discovery rate at the same time, according to our simulation studies.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>High-dimensional linear state space models for dynamic microbial interaction networks.</title>
      <link>/post/high-dimensional-linear-state-space-models-for-dynamic-microbial-interaction-networks/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/high-dimensional-linear-state-space-models-for-dynamic-microbial-interaction-networks/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker: Debosmita Kundu&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week Debosmita Kundu will talk about a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5687744/&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt;. Here is the &lt;a href=&#34;/slides/slides_kundu.pdf&#34;&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt;. Brief summary is below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt;
High-dimensional linear state space models for dynamic microbial interaction networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowledge of the abundance of bacteria—which are the predominant members of the human microbiome—in time-course studies along with appropriate mathematical models will allow us to identify key dynamic interaction networks within the microbiome. However, the high-dimensional nature of these data poses significant challenges to the development of such mathematical models. We propose a high-dimensional linear State Space Model (SSM) with a new Expectation-Regularization-Maximization (ERM) algorithm to construct a dynamic Microbial Interaction Network (MIN). System noise and measurement noise can be separately specified through SSMs. In order to deal with the problem of high-dimensional parameter space in the SSMs, the proposed new ERM algorithm employs the idea of the adaptive LASSO-based variable selection method so that the sparsity property of MINs can be preserved. We performed simulation studies to evaluate the proposed ERM algorithm for variable selection. The proposed method is applied to identify the dynamic MIN from a time-course vaginal microbiome study of women.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Paper Review: Estimation of Cell Lineage Trees by Maximum-likelihood Phylogenetics</title>
      <link>/post/paper-review-estimation-of-cell-lineage-trees-by-maximum-likelihood-phylogenetics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/paper-review-estimation-of-cell-lineage-trees-by-maximum-likelihood-phylogenetics/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker: Dr. Karin Dorman&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Motivated by the DREAM &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.synapse.org/#!Synapse:syn20692755/wiki/595096&#34;&gt;challenge&lt;/a&gt;, Dr. Dorman is going to review a 2019 &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/1904.00117.pdf&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt;. There is also a Science &lt;a href=&#34;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/353/6298/aaf7907.long&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; that introduces the general background. The title and abstract of the 2019 paper is below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Estimation of cell lineage trees bymaximum-likelihood phylogenetics&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CRISPR technology has enabled large-scale cell lineage tracing for complex multicellular organismsby mutating synthetic genomic barcodes during organismal development. However, these sophisticated biological tools currently use ad-hoc and outmoded computational methods to reconstructthe cell lineage tree from the mutated barcodes. Because these methods are agnostic to thebiological mechanism, they are unable to take full advantage of the data’s structure. We propose astatistical model for the mutation process and develop a procedure to estimate the tree topology,branch lengths, and mutation parameters by iteratively applying penalized maximum likelihoodestimation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Paired-end reads merging using pair-hidden Markov model</title>
      <link>/post/paired-end-reads-merging-using-pair-hidden-markov-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/paired-end-reads-merging-using-pair-hidden-markov-model/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Author: Shofi Andari&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A DNA fragment, in Illumina paired-end (PE) sequencing, is read from both ends, resulting forward and backward reads. This can be seen as a challenge and also an opportunity to infer the DNA fragment by merging the information from the PE reads, where the alignment is involved is part of the solution.
The challenge is identifying the replicate nucleotides and combining the information. There have been numerous tools developed for merging PE reads (and this area of research is still growing). Many of these methods ignore the possibility of sequencing indels, which are rare but not impossible, or assign penalties more consistent with evolutionary rates than Illuminated sequencing rates for indels. All of these methods either ignore the quality scores or assume they can be interpreted as PHRED error probabilities. Preliminary evidence suggests that using quality based substitution penalties and appropriate indel penalties in alignment can improve read pair merging. We propose the idea of PE read merging via HMM. The alignment state is the hidden information at each site. The possible hidden states include non overlapping end regions and deletions, insertions, and match base pairs in the overlap region. We are building the scheme under a pair-hidden Markov model (pair-HMM) using the Baum-Welch algorithm to estimate the parameters, and the Viterbi algorithm to find the most likely alignment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Constrained Newton method for transcript quantification project Salmon</title>
      <link>/post/constrained-newton-method-for-transcript-quantification-project-salmon/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/constrained-newton-method-for-transcript-quantification-project-salmon/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Author: Lingnan Yuan&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract: RNA-seq is a deep sequencing technique used to analyze the transcriptome. One of the major interest of transcriptome is the gene expression estimation. The transcript quantification can be realized in two steps, the first is to align the reads into the transcriptome, the second step is to estimate the abundance of transcripts. The well-known project Salmon used EM algorithm in the second step, which is slow as the ridge shaped likelihood gets flat. We are considering to speed up using newton method instead.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistical Tools on Haplotype Phasing for Diploids and Polyploids</title>
      <link>/post/statistical-tools-on-haplotype-phasing-for-diploids-and-polyploids/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/statistical-tools-on-haplotype-phasing-for-diploids-and-polyploids/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;This top is a good fit for people who want to know about newly developed statistical and computational methods in haplotype phasing (not only for diploids but also for polyploids)! 2 recent papers related to this topic will be discussed. Here is the summary &lt;a href=&#34;/slides/Hap_Phasing.pdf&#34;&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below are links to the papers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Edge, P. et al. (2017) HapCUT2: robust and accurate haplotype assembly for diverse sequencing technologies. Genome Res., 27, 801–812. &lt;a href=&#34;https://genome.cshlp.org/content/27/5/801.full.pdf&#34;&gt;URL&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;He D., Saha S., Finkers R., Parida L., 2018. Efficient algorithms for polyploid haplotype phasing. BMC Genomics 19: 110. &lt;a href=&#34;https://bmcgenomics.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12864-018-4464-9&#34;&gt;URL&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Model-Based Clustering of Illumina Microbiome Amplicon Sequence</title>
      <link>/post/model-based-clustering-of-illumina-microbiome-amplicon-sequence/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/model-based-clustering-of-illumina-microbiome-amplicon-sequence/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Author: Xiyu Peng&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next-generation amplicon sequencing is a powerful tool for investigating microbial communities. One main challenge is to distinguish true biological variants from errors caused by PCR and sequencing. In the traditional analysis pipeline, such errors are eliminated by clustering reads within a sequence similarity threshold, usually 97%, and constructing operational taxonomic units (OTUs). However, the arbitrary threshold can lead to low resolution and high false-positive rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, we introduce AmpliCI, a reference-free model-based method for rapidly resolving the number, abundance, and identity of error-free sequences in massive Illumina amplicon datasets. AmpliCI takes into account quality information and allows the data, rather than an arbitrary threshold or an external database, to drive the conclusion. AmpliCI estimates a mixture model, using a greedy strategy to gradually select error-free sequences while approximately maximizing the likelihood. In a simulation study, our method achieves better accuracy than competing methods, especially in communities of closely related species. AmpliCI also shows comparable or better accuracy than other methods when analyzing real mock datasets.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First Statistical Genetics Group Meeting</title>
      <link>/post/first-statistical-genetics-group-meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/first-statistical-genetics-group-meeting/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;It is the first statistical genetics group meeting at ISU, attendees from different departments (STAT, BCB ,etc) with silimar interests in statistics modelling in genetics came together, got to know each other and talked about their ideas regard to this area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr.Dorman talked about statistical modeling in genetics on three aspects: genetics, computing and statistics. The slides can be found &lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We decided to make this group as a place for people to learn influential and trending methods in statistical model in genetics and also a place to present our own research. Hope we all enjoy this process :))&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
